Once upon a time...
there was
a quiet little village...
in the French countryside...
whose people believed
in tranquilite.
Tranquility.
Come Holy Ghost
Creator come
From Thy bright
heavenly throne
Come take possession
of our souls
And make them all Thine own
Far from us drive our...
If you lived in this village...
you understood
what was expected of you.
You knew your
place in the scheme of things.
And if you happened to forget,
someone would help remind you.
The season of Lent is upon us.
This is, of course,
a time of abstinence.
Hopefully,
also a time of reflection.
Above all,
let this be for us a time...
a time of sincere penitence.
it is a time
to stand up and be counted.
In this village...
if you saw something
you weren't supposed to see...
you learned
to look the other way.
This is a time for Christ.
When you reflect,
he knows what you reflect on.
If by chance...
your hopes
had been disappointed...
you learned
never to ask for more.
He knows for what
you must be forgiven.
So in this Year of Our Lord,
1959, things...
So,
through good times and bad...
famine and feast...
the villagers held fast
to their traditions.
Until...
one winter day...
a sly wind
blew in from the north.
Where will we find truth?
Where do we start looking?
We will find it...
Who the hell are you?
Oh, uh...
We're here about the patisserie.
We'd like to rent it...
and the apartment above.
Where are you from?
Well, we lived in Andalucia
for a while.
Let me see.
Before that, Vienna...
and before that...
-Athens.
-Pavia.
Pantoufle hated it there.
Pantoufle is her kangaroo.
But he can't hop.
Bad leg. War injury, huh?
I'll expect you to keep it
in good condition.
What a nice town this is.
Don't you think so, Mama?
It's a lovely town.
Mama, Pantoufle wants to know
how long we can stay.
Oh, tell Pantoufle
not to worry.
Time for bed.
What story tonight?
Pantoufle wants to hear
about grandmere and grandpere.
Not tonight, Anouska.
You always say that.
Tell about
grandmere and grandpere.
Not tonight.
How about the princess
and the pirates?
OK.
Prepare to fire!
All hands on deck!
Ready, aim...
fire!
Forgive the intrusion.
it's a pleasure.
Sorry, monsieur.
-Pirate attack.
-Of course.
What is your name?
Anouk. What's yours?
I am the Comte de Reynaud
at your service.
A real one?
Like the Comte de Monte Cristo?
Ah-ah !
He was not a real one.
To what do we owe
the honor of your visit?
Well, as mayor of Lansquenet...
I want to welcome you
to the community...
and to invite you to worship
with us at mass on Sunday.
That's very kind of you,
but actually we don't attend.
We're glad to be
so near the church, though.
We'll enjoy
singing with the bells.
The bells are not intended
as an entertainment, Madame.
They are a solemn call
to worship for-
Mademoiselle.
I beg your pardon?
I've never been married...
but feel free to call me Vianne.
I hope you'll stop by when
I open for business next week.
Yes.
Yes, opening a patisserie
during the holy Lenten fast.
I could imagine better timing.
Oh, but it's not going
to be a patisserie.
Then what do you intend to-
It's a surprise.
It was sweet of you to drop by.
The Comte de Reynaud...
was a student of history,
and therefore a patient man.
He trusted the wisdom
of generations past.
Like his ancestors, he watched
over the little village...
and led by his own example-
hard work, modesty...
self discipline.
I have completed
the 18th Century.
Madame Clairmont.
Your letter to the editor,
Monsieur le Comte.
This paragraph about family
and tradition, it's...
it's beautiful.
Oh ! Ha ha.
Well, thank you.
I value your opinion.
May I ask...
have you been in contact
with your mother recently?
Why?
She seems to have
rented out the patisserie.
Oh.
I haven't talked to my mother
in quite a while.
I'm sorry.
I did not mean to pry.
Oh, don't be silly.
I have no secrets from you.
How is the comtesse
enjoying Venice?
The comtesse?
Oh, she's fine, thank you.
Yes,
she's enjoying it very much.
Venice.
I heard she was
some kind of radical.
I heard she's an atheist.
What's that?
Don't know.
Come on, Charly.
Come on.
You should be more careful!
-So sorry, Madame.
-I'm sorry.
Are you all right?
I'm fine, I'm fine.
I'm sorry. Do you want
to come in and sit down?
Please don't
trouble yourself. I'm fine.
No, it's no trouble.
I'm Vianne Rocher.
Caroline Clairmont.
I'm the daughter
of your landlady.
This is my son Luc.
Hello.
And this is my Anouk.
Come in, please,
where it's warm.
Try this.
I bet you've never
had hot chocolate...
made from
a 2,000-year-old recipe.
Thank you, but no. Luc.
No.
What's this?
What do you see, Madame,
in this?
Sorry?
What does it look like to you?
Just say the first thing
that comes into your mind.
Um...
A woman riding a wild horse?
Ha !
-Ooh !
-Oh, silly answer.
Oh, no.
There are no silly answers.
The pepper triangle,
that's for you.
A tiny hint of chili pepper...
to play against the sweetness.
Tangy, adventurous.
What do you see?
I see teeth.
I see blood...
and a skull.
Very dark.
Bitter chocolate.
That's your favorite.
Which will
have to wait five weeks more.
Lent. Thank you.
We must run along.
It's been nice to meet you.
My pleasure.
Pantoufle, come on!
Pirate attack!
How much are
those chili things, please?
4.50 a box.
Could you put a ribbon on it?
Mm-hmm.
Then I can pretend
they are from my husband.
Of course.
Josephine Muscat.
She waltzes to her own tune.
And these are for your husband-
unrefined coco nips
from Guatemala-
to awaken the passions.
You've obviously
never met my husband.
never tried these.
Don't be pathetic.
Luc.
You've got a tiny error
in problem six-Oh!
Luc! Oh.
It's nothing.
It already stopped.
Mother, the new teacher...
wants us to correct
our own mistakes.
I didn't tell you
how to correct the mistake...
I just told you
that you made one.
Not hungry, Monsieur le Comte?
The Lenten fast, Madame Rivet.
Are you not supposed
to eat something?
It's all right. Leave it.
Hello.
May I help you?
It's expensive.
I don't waste money.
I have a knack for
guessing people's favorites.
These are your favorites.
Am I right?
On the house.
I think I'd better-
Well...
This certainly is different.
Yes. Very different.
Look at that.
Oh !
Oh. I'm so sorry.
Bonjour, Monsieur Blerot.
Bonjour, Madame Audel.
No. Not that way, Charly.
Come on.
Come in ! Please.
Come on, boy.
I've got something for you.
What's your name?
Charly.
He's fourteen years old.
That's ninety-eight
in human years.
No, I meant your name.
Oh ! Guillaume Blerot.
You're very kind.
He has so few pleasures left.
Would you care...
Would you care to buy...
something special
for your lady friend?
Lady friend?
The lovely woman
your dog was so fond of,
Oh.
Her favorite
is chocolate seashells.
That's my guess.
Oh, no. I mustn't.
Madame Audel is in mourning
for her husband.
Oh, I'm sorry.
When did he pass away?
The war. German grenade.
Hmm.
Well, it's been fifteen years
since the war, so...
Not that war.
Monsieur Audel was killed
on January 12, 1917.
It was quite a blow
to Madame Audel.
Apparently so.
-Hmm.
Bonjour, Mesdames!
Bonjour, Monsieur le Comte.
I wish all my tenants...
were as reliable as you,
Madame Drou.
How is the comtesse
enjoying ltaly?
Uh...She may be
extending her trip.
Ah, very nice.
Have either of you seen
the new shop across the square?
The chocolaterie? Yes.
Shameless, isn't it?
The sheer nerve of the woman...
opening a chocolaterie
just in time for Lent.
The woman is brazen.
My heart
goes out to that poor...
illegitimate child of hers.
Mmm.
Bonjour.
You ain't nothin'
but a hound dog
Cryin' all the time
You ain't nothin'
but a hound dog
Cryin' all the time
Well, you ain't never
caught no rabbit
You ain't no friend of mine
Ooh, yeah !
A new addition to the liturgy?
I have a weakness
for American music...
Monsieur le Comte.
How long have you been with us,
Pere Henri?
It will be five weeks.
Your predecessor, Pere Michel,
he was with us for five decades.
Yes, well...
I only pray I can live up
to Pere Michel's example.
Yes, that's my prayer also.
I looked at your sermon,
as you requested.
I've made one or two notes.
You're very kind.
Not at all.
Oh, one more thing.
If you haven't seen
the new chocolaterie...
perhaps you might
like to take a look.
It's important
to know one's enemy.
Don't you think?
Hey, where's my kiss?
Watch where you're going !
Excuse me!
Hello. Morning.
What's the decor,
Early Mexican Brothel?
No! If I need help,
I'll ask for it.
What do you see in it?
Not a damn thing.
Come on. It's a game.
What do you see?
I see a cranky old woman
too tired to play games.
Hmm. I've got
just the thing for you.
That little girl
of yours, does she mind it?
Mind what?
The way you move her
from place to place.
Oh. She's doing fine.
I think it's good for her.
Seeing new places,
meeting new people.
Your cinnamon looks rancid.
Well, it's not cinnamon.
It's a special kind
of chili pepper.
Chili pepper in hot chocolate?
Mm-hmm.
it'll give you a lift .
It tastes like...
I don't know.
Hop, hop, hop!
I'm your kangaroo now!
Stop it!
Stop it! Unh !
Anouk! In this school,
we are civilized.
We do not strike one another!
But they insulted Pantoufle!
I don't care.
Didi, Dedou, come along !
And be quiet.
Where's Pantoufle?
My mother says
you don't have a father.
Sure I do.
We just don't know who he is.
I was out all night with him.
We swam naked in the Tannes.
At dawn, when I returned
to my house in my bed...
my mother poked her head
in and said...
"Wake up sleepyhead."
She had no idea I'd been gone.
Sure you didn't
put booze in there?
Nah. Something better.
Perhaps you should
give it to my daughter.
Melt that chilly
disposition of hers.
You and Caroline have a problem?
Do we have a problem?
She won't let me
see my grandson.
I'm cut off from him.
Why is that?
Armande, why is that?
Oh, I'm a bad influence.
'Cause I don't like her treating
him like a trained poodle.
I swear, that boy doesn't piss
without her permission.
Ever since her husband died...
she's been so...
The way she frets
and fusses over that boy.
If only she'd let him run,
let him breathe...
let him live.
But she worries
that he will overexert himself.
Not much danger of that.
She won't even let
the poor kid ride a bicycle.
Do you think
he'd like to see you?
Do you have more of
those bean thingies, please?
Oh, sure.
How many do you want?
How many have you got?
Jack of hearts is a better
hunter than you, eh?
Shoots the trump
from right out under your nose.
Are you Serge Muscat?
The one and only.
What's your pleasure?
-Is your wife here?
-Josephine?
Well, it depends what
you want with Josephine.
Oh, she left this at my shop.
Well, let me have it.
I'll give it to her.
Oh, no. I'll give it
to her myself, thanks.
But the game's not over yet.
Do you want to play?
You know Belote?
Of course I do.
Sit down.
Josephine.
What do you want?
You forgot this.
To be your friend.
I don't have friends.
Does Serge know you're here?
Does it matter?
Do me a favor.
Try one of these rose creams.
Tell me if you think it's
a little heavy on the Cointreau.
Josephine!
I'm coming !
He talks about you.
He says you're indecent.
He says you're an influence.
You're a bad influence
for someone like me-
I don't have to listen to a word
your husband has to say.
No, not Serge.
Not him.
Reynaud, the mayor.
He...he talks about you.
Time to go.
Look what I won.
That's good. Come on.
Luc, mind if I take a peek?
Oh, um...
It's not really...
Show me.
Well, I exaggerated
the angle of the head.
You draw beautifully.
What's your going rate?
What?
To do a portrait.
How much would you charge?
Oh, I...
I couldn't.
I'm not really a...
Fifty francs?
Sound reasonable?
lt'd be great.
When could you come by my shop?
I'm-I'm really sorry, but...
the comte forbids it.
He spoke to Mama this morning...
and a lot of others.
Whatever you say.
I wish I could. I really do.
Thanks for showing me
your drawing.
Wait.
Am I breaking any laws?
Tell me?
Am I hurting anyone?
You're asking me my opinion?
What exactly have you been
telling people about me?
Only the truth, mademoiselle.
Well...
if you're expecting me...
to just shrivel up
and blow away...
you're going to be
highly disappointed.
Let me try and put this
into perspective for you.
The first Comte de Reynaud...
expelled all the radical
Huguenots from this village.
You and your truffles
present a far lesser challenge.
You'll be
out of business by Easter.
I promise you that.
How long have you
been standing here?
I forgot to pay you
for something the other day.
I'm sorry.
No, it was a gift.
No. People talk.
No, people would lie about me.
I don't steal.
Not on purpose. I-
Yes, I know.
It's nice to see you.
Would you like to come in
for some chocolate?
This is for you.
How sweet of you.
Thank you.
Hmm, it's lovely.
I heard you don't go to church.
That's right.
You won't last long here.
People talk.
Oh, sorry.
I'm behaving badly, aren't I?
No, it's OK.
You don't misbehave here.
It's just not done,
did you know that?
If you don't go to Confession...
or if you don't
dig your flower beds...
or if you don't pretend...
that you want nothing
more in your life...
than to serve your husband
three meals a day...
and give him children
and vacuum under his ass...
then-then you're crazy.
You must think I'm stupid
to stay with him.
No, I don't think you're stupid.
Well, I am. I'm weak.
I don't love my husband,
and I lie.
Things could be different
for you, Josephine.
Serge doesn't run the world.
He might as well.
Is that what you believe?
I know it.
Then it must be true.
My mistake.
You make the most
wonderful chocolate.
Pantoufle wants
to hear the story...
of grandmere and grandpere.
Ohh !
Don't say, "Not tonight."
You always say, "Not tonight."
All right, all right.
Your grandfather...
George Rocher...
was the young apothecary
of the town of Aulus-les-Bains.
it was Anouk's favorite story.
Always told in the same words.
George was honest,
prosperous...
and trusted by his customers.
But George was not content.
He felt there
should be more to life...
than dispensing liver oil.
In the spring of 1927...
the Societe Pharmeceutique...
formed an expedition
to Central America...
to study
the medicinal properties...
of certain natural compounds.
George was the expedition's
most eager volunteer.
But his adventure
took a turn he did not expect.
One night, he was invited
to drink unrefined cacao...
with a pinch of chili.
The very same drink
the ancient Maya...
used in their sacred
ceremonies.
The Maya believed
cacao held the power...
to unlock hidden yearnings...
and reveal destinies.
And so it was
that George first saw Chitza.
Now, George had been raised
a good Catholic...
but in his romance
with Chitza...
he was willing
to slightly bend the rules...
of Christian courtship.
The tribal elders
tried to warn George about her.
She was one of the wanderers.
Her people moved
with the North Wind...
from village to village...
dispensing ancient remedies...
never settling down.
Not a good choice for a bride.
George did not
heed their warning...
and for a while,
it seemed that he and Chitza...
might lead a happy life
together in France.
Alas, the clever North Wind
had ot her plans.
One morning,
George awoke to discover...
that Chitza
and the little girl Vianne...
had gone away.
Mother and daughter...
were fated to wander
from village to village...
dispensing
ancient cacao remedies...
traveling with the wind.
Just as Chitza's people
had done...
for generations.
Just as Chitza's people...
had done for generations.
Will it just go on forever?
Night, Mama.
I appreciate your coming in,
Armande.
What's so important
that I had to postpone my nap?
I've got some chocolate cake.
Grandmother.
Grandmother...bonjour.
May I...
Would you like a cup of...?
No, thank you.
I'm just here to do a portrait.
Mm-hmm.
Whose?
Yours, actually.
Is the light OK
where she's sitting?
I have something for you, boy.
I've been carrying it around
since your last birthday.
It's a book of poetry.
Oh.
Thank you.
You don't like poetry?
Oh, no. Of course I do.
Yes.
Neither do I.
It's not that kind of poetry.
And in a moment of weakness...
I prayed to the Virgin Mother...
to soothe Charly's soul
in his hour of suffering.
You understand an animal
has no immortal soul.
I understand, mon pere.
Yet you flout God's law.
I'm weak and a sinner.
What else?
lmpure thoughts.
The woman
who runs the chocolaterie.
Vianne Rocher?
She suggested
I buy chocolate seashells...
for the widow Audel.
And, well...
I guess that got me to thinking
about the widow Audel.
At her age? At your age?
Yes. And yes.
And just what were you doing
in a chocolaterie during Lent?
It was for Charly.
Again you flout God's law.
Well, but if Charly
has no soul...
then there's no harm
in him breaking Lent.
Isn't that so, mon pere?
Ten Hail Marys,
twenty Our Fathers.
"Will she never have done,
then...
"that ghoul queen of
a million dead bodies?
"I see myseIf again...
"skin rotten
with mud and pest...
"worms in my armpits
and in my hair."
It's perfectly wretched,
isn't it?
Perfectly.
Would you like some cake?
Ahem. I'm not supposed to.
Don't worry so much
about not supposed to.
Hmm?
Live a little.
Oh, her hair appointment's
almost done.
I have to go.
-What about my picture?
-Next time.
Thank you for the cake.
Don't look so damn pleased
with yourself.
Stay here.
I did it.
I did it. He...
He was so drunk.
He woke up.
He saw me packing, but...
So he tried to come after me...
but I had already tied his feet
with his belt, and...
Ha ha ha ha ha.
Boom ! Right on his face.
Right there
on his big, red face.
It is so stupid, isn't it?
I never blame him.
Sometimes I even forget
what really happened.
Now, now, now.
Shh.
I saved her!
You remember her father
collaborated with the Germans?
Nobody wanted to touch her.
Except for me.
And this is the way
she repays me?!
Your anger is understandable.
Anger?
Everybody's laughing at me!
That is not your concern.
Your concern is
the sacrament of marriage.
Yeah, of course.
The sacrament.
Dip the ganshbe
into the white chocolate.
Like this?
Good.
Yes, shake it, a little.
Put it on the parchment sheet.
You're doing great.
Oh. I'll be right back.
Oh. Good morning.
Can I interest you
in some Nipples of Venus?
Rumor has it that you are
harboring Madame Muscat.
Is that true?
You make her sound
like a fugitive.
She is a fugitive,
from her marriage vows...
which have been
sanctified by God.
Josephine?
Come out here a minute.
Let His Radiance
have a look at you, hmm?
Is that sanctified
enough for you?
it's not the first time.
I'm truly sorry.
You should have come to me.
Your husband will be made
to repent for this.
Tell him to repent
on someone else's head.
Come on. In !
Monsieur le Comte!
I'm going to make
an example of you.
In there. He's ready.
Well, but confession
must be made...
in the spirit of contrition.
Have you come
in the spirit of contrition?
Contrition, yes.
He's ready.
Licentiousness,
idolatry, sorcery...
gluttony, and drunkenness.
Correct.
And what are the three
conditions for mortal sin?
Serge?
Mortal sin...
is sin whose object is...
committed by...
deliberate...consequence.
Incorrect. Didi?
Mortal sin is sin
whose object is grave matter...
which is committed
with full knowledge...
and deliberate consent.
Correct.
So, how do you know...
if the coverture
is properly tempered?
You check to see
if it's at body temperature.
Then you dip
the palette knife...
to see that the coverture
hardens on it evenly.
Correct.
Closer.
In the village, time passed.
And the chocolaterie
did not go out of business.
The Comte de Reynaud...
felt himself being drawn
into a strange crusade.
His struggle to transform Serge
into a gentleman...
became more
than an act of good will.
it became a test...
a holy war between chateau...
and chocolaterie.
Each time, I...
I tell myself
it's the last time.
But then I...
I get a whiff
of a hot chocolate.
Or those moon things.
Chocolate seashells.
So small, so plain, so innocent.
I thought,
just one little taste...
it can't do any harm.
But it turned out
that they were filled...
with rich, sinful...
Buttery filling...
and it melts,
God forgive me...
it melts ever-so-slowly
on your tongue...
and tortures you with pleasure.
Against You alone,
have I sinned...
and done what is evil
in Your sight.
Indeed I was born guilty...
a sinner when my mother
conceived me.
You desire truth
in the inward being...
therefore teach me wisdom
in my secret heart.
Now, the comte was no fool.
Though he hoped
to redeem Serge...
he knew that
this redemption alone...
would not be enough...
to regain control
over the village.
He understood
that some larger lesson...
needed to be taught.
Some greater problem...
needed to be identified
and solved.
Little did the comte suspect
that his greater problem...
would arrive
one quiet afternoon...
in the dull green waters
of the river Tannes.
You're it!
Hey, look!
I'm over here!
You've never really
told me what the problem is...
between you and Caroline.
'Cause it's none of
your damn business.
I'm an embarrassment to her.
I swear, I read dirty books.
I eat and drink what I like.
And sin of sins...
I refuse to go to Les Mimosas.
When I was a kid,
we called it Le Mortoir.
it's a nursing home for old...
It's in Toulouse.
Mmm.
Caroline loves
the thought of a nurse...
with a clipboard
recording my bowel movements.
Mama, Mama, come quick!
They're here!
They've come to Lansquenet!
-Slow down, Anouk. Who's here?
-Pirates!
-Why can't we stay?
-Come on !
But why can't we stay?
OK, enough.
But, Mama,
just a little bit.
Come on.
Hello. How are you?
Anybody got a sweet tooth?
I bet he's the captain.
Anouk, don't do that.
Anouk, don't do that, please.
-How do you do?
-Sorry.
I'd like to apologize.
For all of us. Sincerely.
What for?
For whatever it is
you're here to accuse us of.
Why would I do that?
Well, because we river rats
are the dregs of society.
With horrible diseases
and criminal impulses.
Sounds terrifying.
Is it true?
It's what you townspeople
always seem to think, isn't it?
This is not my town.
Sorry.
Well, then,
what do you want?
Are you here to save us?
Are you
the Catholic Aid Society?
French Family League?
Communist Workers?
Which idea are you selling?
Chocolate.
I'm sorry, chocolate?
What's a river rat?
Is it like a pirate?
Yeah, you could say that.
You could.
Have a look
at my treasure chest.
Oh.
Let me guess, they're for sale.
As a matter of fact,
they are.
For a mere thirty francs apiece.
You laugh? I can get fifty
for them in Paris.
Then go to Paris.
We'll take two, please.
You'll take two?
Yes, please, absolutely.
OK.
I don't know
if I have the right change.
Just a minute.
They're beautiful.
Ireland's finest.
Thanks.
Thank you. Listen...
I should probably warn you.
You make friends with us,
you'll make enemies of others.
That a promise?
It's a guarantee.
What's he up to?
Maybe he's joining the circus.
Sorry, we're closed !
Josephine, you look different.
So do you.
I just want to tell you
that I am so sorry.
For everything.
But I've changed.
You see,
God has made me a new man.
I ask you, I beg you...
please accept my apology.
I accept.
I promise, from now on,
everything will be different.
Everything already
is different, Serge.
Well, I mean,
when you come home.
Home?
Thanks for the apology.
The flowers are lovely.
No, please don't, Josephine.
We are still married
in the eyes of God.
Then he must be blind.
The council
has no legal authority...
to force them to move.
The riverbank is public land.
The mayor wishes
to say a few words.
If I may...
ladies and gentlemen
of the council.
These people are
rootless, godless drifters.
Theirs is the way
of slovenly pleasure.
They would contaminate
the spirit of our quiet town.
The innocence of our children.
Now, the chairman of the council
is quite right.
We cannot force them to leave.
But we can help them
to understand...
that they are not welcome.
Josephine?
Josephine, you think
you can just walk out on me?
You stupid woman!
Worthless cow!
You're nothing without me.
You can't even use a skillet!
Can't even put
a goddamn meal on the table.
He's inside.
He's here. Oh, God.
I need to talk to you.
Please open the door.
I know-
-Mama!
-Come help me!
Open the door.
I just want to talk to you.
Go sleep it off, Serge!
Ah, you shut up,
you bitch!
You've caused enough
trouble already!
You-
Open this door!
Mama !
Aah ! Aah !
Oh, my God!
Stay away from me.
-Come here now!
-Aah !
Why, you meddling bitch !
You-
Who says I can't use a skillet?
Bonjour, monsieur.
Bonjour.
Wonderful.
Come on.
Up. Come on. Up.
His skull can't be
as thick as we thought.
it was like swatting a fly.
Ohh. The worst is over.
He found out
what you're made of.
So did I.
-Hi.
-Hey.
How long have we got?
She's at the hairdresser
for an hour.
Fuffi?
Fuffi.
I'm so sorry, but I have
to break the appointment.
Is something wrong?
No. I volunteered
to distribute these.
I promised the comte I'd have
them out by the end of the day.
Count me in.
Not that I expect any of them
to stop by for a hairstyle.
it's not just that.
The comte feels
we must stand firm.
We cannot trust these people.
Before you know it,
they'll be doing jobs for food.
They'll be begging
at our doors.
Not at this door.
Good, Fuffi, good.
Rub, rub.
Rub harder. Rub.
Rub. Rub.
Rub it. Hard.
Keep your head still.
-Aha!
-Bravo!
Hello, Caroline.
If you want to
blame someone, blame me-
corrupting him with cocoa.
Oh, how dare you, Mother.
He's happy. He's fine.
Look at him.
Mama, I-
Well, what about you, Mother?
Are you fine?
I bet she has conveniently
forgotten to tell you.
Carol.
Why don't you show them,
Mother?
Are you afraid to?
Why don't you show?
Insulin shots.
She has diabetes-
very advanced.
She could be blind
within a year.
Yeah. Couldn't you
call me a drug addict?
It sounds a lot more glamorous.
And you-
you sit here feeding her sweets.
There are worse ways to die.
Why don't you
just give her rat poison?
it would be faster.
Carol has a flair for drama.
She needs to be in a place
where she can be taken care of.
Le Mortoir?
I'd rather be in Hell.
Ah.
You may get there, Mother.
Luc, come with me.
I don't want to.
He's happy here.
It's good for him.
I will decide what is good
for my son, Madame Muscat.
Give me another.
It's my life.
Let me enjoy what's left of it.
Fill 'er up.
Armande, why didn't you tell me?
Is this a chocolaterie,
or is it a confessional?
Don't you dare pity me.
Sorry, we're closed.
She just wants a soda water.
I don't serve animals.
Right.
-Hello.
-Hi.
I just made a fresh
batch of monduon.
Anybody interested?
My tummy hurts.
I've got just the thing
for that. Come in.
What about boycotting
immorality, then?
Come in.
An old remedy.
From the cocoa tree.
Tastes strange.
Mmm. Maybe your daddy
would like a taste.
He's not my daddy.
He's my pony.
Here. it's a lot
better than those leaves.
Tastes good.
-Come on.
Pantoufle wants to meet you.
He's my kangaroo.
Go ahead. It's your favorite.
What makes you so sure?
Go on. Taste it.
Hmm.
That's fantastic.
Oh, thanks.
I have a knack for guessing.
It's good-
not my favorite.
Sorry?
All right.
Thanks very much.
You know, I could fix that,
if you like.
Not with glass, but...
I can make you a nice
strong one out of wood.
That's nice of you...
but I insist on paying you
for your work.
That makes two of us, then.
Bye.
Thanks again.
She's laughing at us.
Now she's got one of those
river people working for her.
Is that a problem?
Christ teaches us-
Look at this.
She's soliciting for stalls
and street performers...
for a fertility celebration
on Easter Sunday.
She's cackling at us.
When are you going to do
something about it?
Oh, there.
What part of Australia
is Pantoufle from?
A small town
outside of Sydney.
What does he eat?
Leaves, bugs...
and worms, of course.
What about chocolate?
Kangaroos don't eat chocolate.
Has he ever tried it?
Have you ever tried chocolate?
He's not interested.
Not interested?
Mr. Pantoufle, you surprise me.
A world traveler
such as yourself...
not interested in new flavors?
You should be ashamed.
I have a very nice
truffle here...
if he wants to try it.
You're wasting your time.
Oh, I'm sorry.
How do you know
you don't like chocolate...
if you refuse to try it?
Do you like worms?
What?
How do you know
if you've never tasted one?
Ha ha !
Ah.
Ew.
Subtle.
Zesty.
Disgusting.
Go on, my little friend.
Be free.
You tricked me.
Satan...
wears many guises.
At times, Satan is
the singer of a lurid song...
you hear on the radio.
At times, the author
of a salacious novel.
At times, the quiet man
lurking in the schoolyard...
asking your children
if he might join their game.
And at times,
the maker of sweet things-
mere trifles.
For what could seem
more harmless...
more innocent...
than chocolate?
A bit of a squeak.
Hey, Guillaume!
I've got something new
Charly's going to love.
Come on, Charly. Come on.
It's me. I should go.
No, it's not you. It's-
Where have you been?
I was worried.
Hey! I'm talking to you.
it's just like
all the other towns.
Anouk.
Just tell me what happened.
Are you Satan's helper?
Well, it's not
easy being different.
Why can't we go to church?
Well, you can if you want,
but it won't make things easier.
Why can't you wear black shoes
like the other mothers?
He's a fine piece of work,
our little nobleman.
No wonder his wife
goes gallivanting off.
She's been in ltaly for months.
Did you know that?
Armande...
the whole town's against me.
What can I do?
Throw me a party.
Ha ha ha ! What?
Wednesday's my 70th.
Let's show the bastards
we're ready to go down dancing.
But a party?
You're not well.
You have to face it.
OK, OK, OK...
But you do this for me,
and I promise...
I'll check into Le Mortoir
the very next morning...
without a care in the world.
If I threw a party in this town,
no one would come.
They don't need to know
who's throwing it.
Armande, listen, I-
No, no, no.
You listen.
I need this.
When I need help, I ask for it.
Boys,
bring me some more wood.
My mother
used to sing that song...
when I couldn't sleep.
And did it help?
I still didn't sleep,
but, yes, it helped.
How's the door?
It squeaks.
-Does it?
-Ha ha !
How's Anouk? Is she well?
Oh, she's better. She's fine.
Good. How are you?
I'm throwing a party...
If anyone shows up.
Thanks.
Who's invited?
A bunch of townspeople.
Tell me something.
Why do you give a damn about...
what these narrow-minded
villagers think?
You're not scared of them,
are you?
Coming to the party or not?
I can't.
There's a boycott
against immorality...
and I must respect that.
That is a problem.
Then, I'll leave you with
this test of your convictions.
What is that?
Your favorite.
My favorite?
Is that right?
-Thank you.
-You're welcome.
I'm undone-
but not my favorite.
Hmm.
I'll come round sometime...
get that squeak
out of your door.
A lot for you.
You see? It's perfect.
Bon appetit, everyone.
Oh!
Ahh.
If the comte finds out...
The comte isn't here.
He wasn't invited.
Is Luc coming?
I'm sure they have other plans.
Luc?
Why are you sleeping?
Hmm?
Are you not feeling well?
Happy birthday, Grandmama.
The invitation said 5:00.
I should have read it
more closely.
If you had, you'd know there
was supposed to be no gifts.
Don't worry so much
about the "supposed to."
Like it?
You made me younger.
Very diplomatic.
Mmm.
I have two announcements.
Shh!
Number one-if you like
what you tasted here...
you're going to love
my chocolate festival on Sunday.
Advertise on your own time.
What's for dessert?
That brings me to number two.
It is my duty to announce...
that there is no dessert
here tonight.
Oh !
No dessert?
Because it's on Roux's boat.
Any complaints, see me.
Monsieur le Comte?
Who's there?
I must speak to you.
You see, Monsieur le Comte?
You see?
There's Josephine,
that stupid cow.
Something must be done, Serge.
Something must be done.
-You done yet?
-Almost.
-Almost?
-Hmm?
Come on, leave it.
You're done.
Come with me.
Come on.
I have chocolates everywhere.
What? You're all right.
Do you think everyone
had a good time?
I'm tired.
Vianne, Roux.
Thanks.
This was...
Thank you.
I'll take you home.
Oh, for God's sake,
don't fuss.
You'll ruin
a perfectly decadent evening.
I'm not partial
to big, sloppy good-byes.
Armande.
I'll take care
of the dishes.
I think I'll sleep
in my chair tonight.
Do you like it?
Taking your home with you
wherever you go?
Yeah. Why not?
Your way must be harder-
each time having to make
a new home from scratch.
Well, maybe this time
I'll get it right.
What do you mean?
Maybe I'll stay.
What?
Don't you ever think
about belonging somewhere?
The price is too high.
You end up caring what
people expect of you.
No.
Is that so terrible?
Having people
expect something of you?
How does Anouk feel about it?
What?
All the moving around.
No, she's fine.
She handles it beautifully.
She makes friends easily.
She has such an unusual...
She hates it.
Vianne.
Vianne, come on.
Come on.
We need more! Hurry up!
Anouk!
Mommy!
Aah!
Anouk!
No!
Jesus!
Come back!
Anouk!
Come back, Vianne!
-Stop!
-No!
-Stop it!
Stop it! Stop it!
-Come back!
-No!
No!
Come on !
Why did you stop me?
It was too late.
Mom!
There she is.
Oh, my God, there she is!
Mama !
Anouska ! I'm coming !
Oh, my God.
You're hurting me.
I just wanted
to make sure that...
Yes, we're OK.
You?
And I came to say...
To say good-bye.
Yes, I know.
What?
Your boat.
You've lost your home.
No.
Just a way to get
from place to place, really.
So, how will you...
I'll manage.
Well...
Vianne...
Listen, I...
I know. I'm sorry.
I'm sorry.
Your papa used to ride this bike
every single morning.
He would have wanted you
to have it.
Just you promise me
you'll never run away again, OK?
Mama, she...
What?
What's wrong, Luc?
Though we cannot know...
Armande Voizin's
last thoughts...
we can hope they were
thoughts of penitence.
We can hope she asked God...
to forgive
the self indulgence...
that aggravated her illness
and caused her death...
and we can pause
to reexamine our own lives.
We can resist those...
who would lead us
into temptation.
Blessed is the one
who endures temptation...
for when he has stood
the test...
Mama...
Can we go home now?
Of course.
Whatever you like, Mama.
Vianne, did you want me...
to start the ganache
for the festival?
Vianne?
Did you-
What are you doing?
Leaving.
First thing in the morning.
Is it because of Armande?
That was not your fault.
It's time, that's all.
This is who I am.
Did you believe
anything you told me?
I could be better?
Was it all a joke?
I have to pack now.
If you leave,
everything will go back...
to the way it always was.
It is the way it always was.
Not for me.
I know how you feel.
Beg your pardon?
I suppose it can't be easy...
having her gone.
Can't seem to get used to it,
no matter how much time.
Ahem. But I...
look forward to her return.
I don't believe anyone
would think less of you...
if you were to say
she was never coming back.
Good night, Paul.
Caroline!
I'm sorry.
I need to talk to you.
Come in.
Monsieur le Comte.
It's all right.
Sorry to bother you,
Monsieur le Comte.
All right.
It was the right thing to do,
wasn't it?
Of course it was.
I know it was.
it's everything with Josephine.
Serge...
What are you talking about?
The fire,
Monsieur le Comte.
I know it was
the right thing to do...
but I can't get rid of
the faces and the screams.
The fire...
The fire was an act of God.
It was me, Monsieur le Comte.
What?
You told me. Remember?
"Something
has to be done, Serge. "
You did, didn't you?
People could have died.
You want
their blood on your hands?
On-on my hands?
Should I go to Pere Henri
and ask for forgiveness?
Listen to me, Serge.
Listen very carefully.
You must leave
this village at once...
and never return.
Why would I leave
my home and my cafe?
Because I'm evicting you,
that's why!
What you have done
puts you beyond anyone's help...
beyond my help, anybody's help!
Now get out!
Unless you will tell the police
what you've done!
Get out! Get out! Get out!
Time to go.
Hmm?
Oh, no.
I'm not going.
Well, it's hard for me, too.
Pantoufle hates this.
Stop that.
Please put it on.
I hate you.
You're entitled.
I said put it on.
Well, then, do it yourself!
I can't!
Get up.
I have a bad leg like Pantoufle.
Stop that. Get up.
Pantoufle can't walk.
I can't walk.
Walk. Walk!
You're hurting me.
Well, stop being...
Let me go!
No!
It's not fair!
Stop it!
I'm not going !
It's-Stop it!
I'm sorry, Mama.
I'm sorry.
Don't worry, Mama.
The next time will be better,
won't it, Mama?
It will.
it will be wonderful.
I'm ready to go now, OK?
Like this, Mama?
That's right.
Is this right?
No, no, you've got to cut
on the corners like this.
So, just stop them.
Higher.
How do you like these almonds?
Are they chopped fine enough?
Are they OK, Vianne?
Christ is risen.
My friends, let this Easter Day
be for us, too, a rebirth.
Let us strive-
No, no, no, no, no, no.
No, don't bury
the word "rebirth."
Let it ring out.
Let this day be
for us, too, a rebirth !
You see, we are extolling
our-our parishioners...
to-to resurrect
their moral awareness.
Hmm? OK, good, good.
T-try again.
I think we've
gone over this enough.
Let's call it a day.
What?
I'm very tired.
Fine, fine.
Well, leave it with me.
I may have one
or two suggestions.
Thank you, Monsieur le Comte-
Just a couple of suggestions.
A revision here and there.
We want it to be perfect
tomorrow, don't we?
-Yes.
We must resist the shallow,
worldly temptations...
of our mortal-No, no.
We must renounce shallow,
worldly temptations...
of our mortal flesh.
Caroline.
All my efforts
have been for nothing.
I've suffered willingly.
I've fasted.
I've hardly eaten for weeks now.
I'm sorry.
I'm sorry,
my suffering is nothing.
It's just that I...
I feel so lost.
I don't know what to do.
Tell me what to do.
Drink this.
lt'll refresh you.
I promise.
Go ahead, drink.
I'm so sorry.
I won't tell a soul.
Hmm.
Better get cleaned up.
Easter Sunday.
The sermon.
I didn't finish it.
I'lI think of something.
I'm not sure what the theme
of my homily today ought to be.
Do I want to speak
of the miracle...
of our Lord's
divine transformation?
Not really, no.
I don't want
to talk about His divinity.
I'd rather talk about
His humanity.
I mean, you know, how he
lived his life here on Earth.
His kindness.
His tolerance.
Listen, here's what I think.
I think we can't go around...
measuring our goodness
by what we don't do.
By what we
deny ourselves...
what we resist...
and who we exclude.
I think we've got
to measure goodness...
by what we embrace...
what we create...
and who we include.
it was certainly not...
the most fiery sermon
Pere Henri would ever preach...
nor the most eloquent.
But the parishioners
felt a new sensation that day.
A lightening of the spirit.
A freedom
from the old tranquilite.
Whoa ! Fantastic!
Monsieur le Comte,
try one of these.
Thank you.
Even the Comte de Reynaud...
felt strangely...
released.
Although, it would take
another six months...
before he'd work up the nerve
to ask Caroline out to dinner.
As for Josephine...
she took over the lease
at the old cafe...
and gave it a new name.
But still
the clever North Wind...
was not satisfied.
The Wind spoke to Vianne...
of towns yet to be visited.
Friends in need,
yet to be discovered.
Battles yet to be fought.
By someone else...next time.
And so it was,
the North Wind grew weary...
and went on its way.
When summer came
to the little village...
a new breeze from the south
blew soft and warm.
Just needed an adjustment.
Hope it'll be better now.
Roux!
My mother
knew Roux's return...
had nothing to do
with a silly old door.
So did I.
I thought you'd never guess.
My favorite, hot chocolate.
I knew that.
As for Pantoufle?
Well, his bad leg
miraculously healed...
and he hopped off
in search of new adventures.
I didn't miss him.